{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During an engagement in this battle, a British officer said to William Birdwood, \"You're not fighting Bashi-Bazouks now\" while defending Pozières [[poh-ZYEHR]]. In his book The World Crisis, Winston Churchill described the dismissal of this battle's planners Ferdinand Foch [[FOHSH]] and Joseph Joffree. The Mark I [[ONE]] Tank was first deployed at this battle, which was launched to relieve pressure from Verdun. For ten points, name this 1916 World War One battle named for a river in Picardy, France, at which the British sustained 420,000 casualties.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Somme",
        "Somme Offensive"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Alexander Martin composed a funerary poem for this man after he was killed at the Battle of Germantown. This man's brother, Abner, served as the second governor of North Carolina, while this man served in the North Carolina General Assembly before becoming an officer. This man, who heavily opposed the Regulator movement, is the namesake of a city that was originally a fort defending the Cumberland River valley. Leading North Carolina's soldiers in the Pennsylvania campaign, for ten points, who was this Revolutionary War general who names a large Tennessee city?",
      "answer": [
        "Francis Nash",
        "Nashville"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man narrated the documentary He Is Not Dimon to You, which was distributed by this man's Anti-Corruption Foundation. This man called his country's largest political faction \"a party of crooks and thieves.\" After recovering from being poisoned, this man returned home from Berlin only to be imprisoned months later. For ten points, name this Russian opposition leader described by The Wall Street Journal as \"the man Vladimir Putin fears most.\"",
      "answer": "Alexei Navalny"
    },
    {
      "question": "One person with this title had his deceased predecessor tried in the Cadaver Synod [[SIN-ahd]] before casting him into a nearby river. That predecessor with this title, Formosus, was later reported to have performed miracles along the banks of the Tiber. A prophecy regarding people with this title dictates that the last one named Peter will oversee the destruction of the \"City of Seven Hills.\" For ten points, what title is given to the \"holder of the Keys of Heaven,\" also known as the Bishop of Rome?",
      "answer": [
        "Pope",
        "Bishop of Rome before mentioned",
        "Supreme Pontiff",
        "Roman Pontiff 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first scenario of this man's campaign in Age of Empires II [[TWO]] is marked by Crucible. That scenario’s introduction claims that this man's group settled at the “head of the Onon River.” A work subtitled “Clan of the Grey Wolf” appears in a Koei series named for this man, in which players can control a faction led by Jamukha. In one game, this man claims, “It is easy to conquer the world on horseback.” For ten points, name this ruler, whose Civilization 6 leader ability is Mongol Horde.",
      "answer": [
        "Genghis Khan",
        "Temujin",
        "pronunciation as ]",
        "]"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A visit to the White House to celebrate this period resulted in a viral dancing video featuring the 106-year old Virginia McLaurin. Maulana Karenga spoke during the first London iteration of this period. At West Virginia State University, a 2020 convocation for this annual period included a keynote given by DeRay McKesson. A predecessor of this annual period was only a week long and included the birthdays of Abraham Lincoln and Frederick Douglass. For ten points, name this celebration observed every February recognizing African-American achievements.",
      "answer": "Black History Month"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country contains the world’s largest ship graveyard in its city of Nouadhibou [[nwah-DEE-boo]], which was previously named for the French Minister of the Colonies, Eugène Étienne. This country's railroad was home to the Choum [[SHOOM]] Tunnel, a \"monument to European stupidity in Africa.\" This country's Banc d’Arguin [[dahr-GAHN]] is the setting of Théodore Géricault's [[zheh-ree-COHS]] The Raft of the Medusa. The White Moors, or Bidan, enslaved many of this country's Haratines, even after slavery was abolished in 1960. Nouakchott [[NWAHK-shaht]] is the capital of, for ten points, what West African nation?",
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Mauritania"
    },
    {
      "question": "Herodotus [[heh-RAH-duh-tis]] said this man died fighting the Massageteans [[mah- sah-geh-TEE-uns]] along the Syr Darya, while another account said he was killed by Queen Tomyris. At the Battle of Thymbra, this man defeated the army of Croesus [[KREE-sus]] and conquered the Lydian kingdom. This man's capital was at Pasargadae [[pah-SAR-gah-deh]], and he established an administrative system of satraps. This ruler's namesake Cylinder tells the story of his repatriation of the Jews after the Babylonian captivity. For ten points, name this founder of the Achaemenid [[ah-KEE-muh-nid]] Persian Empire.",
      "answer": [
        "Cyrus the Great",
        "Cyrus II of Persia",
        "Cyrus the Elder 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's half-brother, Edward, was killed at Corfe Castle. This man, who created juries in his Wantage [[WAHN-tidge]] law code, paid gafol tributes for peace on the advice of Sigeric the Serious. At Andover, this man sponsored the confirmation of Olaf Tryggvason as a Christian. Gunhilde, and possibly Pallig Tokesen, were killed in the St. Brice's Day Massacre, which this man ordered, prompting an invasion by Sweyn [[SVEN]] Forkbeard. Losing to the Vikings at Maldon, for ten points, who was this \"poorly advised\" King of England?",
      "answer": "Æthelred the Unready"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president claimed that the passage of a Civil Rights Bill would be an act “against the white race.” Landowners with property valuations exceeding $20,000 were surprisingly pardoned after being barred from giving oaths of allegiance under this man’s presidency. This one-term president was a former military governor of Tennessee who many thought would engage in Radical Reconstruction. For ten points, name this 17th president who previously served as vice president under Abraham Lincoln.",
      "answer": "Andrew Johnson 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1995, the Armed Islamic Group of Algeria targeted public transportation in this country. This country's most deadly terrorist attack targeted a soccer stadium and a theatre at which the Eagles of Death Metal were playing. In 2015, al-Qaeda gunmen targeted the offices of Charlie Hebdo in this country. For ten points, name this country whose Gendarmerie [[zhahn-dar-meh-REE]] and National Police share responsibility for counterterrorism operations.",
        "answer": "France or French Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "On November 13, 2015, ninety people were killed by terrorists at this Paris theatre which opened in 1865 and whose name refers to a Jacques Offenbach operetta.",
        "answer": "Bataclan Theatre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Outsized credit default swaps by an employee of this bank known as the “London Whale” resulted in roughly $6 billion in losses for it. The merger of this bank with Bank One resulted in the hiring of Jamie Dimon as its CEO. For a total price of $236 million, this bank acquired the once fifth-largest investment bank, Bear Stearn. Founded by a man who bailed out the U.S. government in 1907 and bought out the Carnegie Steel Corporation, for ten points, what is this bank, partly named for an early twentieth-century financier?",
        "answer": "JPMorgan Chase & Co"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jamie Dimon is one of many influential MBAs to attend the Boston graduate business school of this university of which J.P. Morgan was a major benefactor.",
        "answer": [
          "Harvard University",
          "Harvard College"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1748 essay by Voltaire praises a translation of this work into English created by George Sale. Barack Obama claimed that this text’s central doctrine “has been woven into the fabric of our country.” A 2014 book by Denise Spellberg examines the influence of this text on one Founding Father. The 2007 swearing-in of Minnesota Congressman Keith Ellison notably involved a translation of this book which was owned by Thomas Jefferson and may have inspired Rashida Tlaib to do the same. For ten points, name this non-Biblical religious book.",
        "answer": "The Quran"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This woman, who succeeded Keith Ellison as Minnesota's Representative from the 5th district, also swore in on the Quran in 2018.",
        "answer": "Ilhan Omar 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Kate Blewett studied neglect under this policy in The Dying Rooms. This policy created the 4-2-1 problem as well as \"little emperor\" syndrome. Shidu bereavement is common under this policy, which created the Heihaizi class of people who do not have identity documents. People moved to Hong Kong to avoid this policy, which was relaxed after the Sichuan earthquake. This policy was inspired by Song Jian at the Chengdu Meeting after he read The Limits to Growth and A Blueprint For Survival. For ten points, name this Chinese population control policy.",
        "answer": "One-Child Policy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2002, Kate Blewett's documentary Kids Behind Bars won the Media Award from this international human rights organization, which itself won the 1977 Nobel Peace Prize.",
        "answer": "Amnesty International"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man lined a wooden cabinet with lightbulbs and referred to it as his “electric light bath.” This man’s brother, William, served as his bookkeeper when he was the head of an institution originally led by Ellen White. This man headed an institution that hosted three eugenics conferences for the Race Betterment Foundation. This superintendent of Battle Creek Sanitarium realized that stale wheat which was rolled created a crispier alternative to dough. For ten points, name this American inventor and creator of cornflakes.",
        "answer": "John Harvey Kellogg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the Battle Creek Sanitarium's most famous patients was this woman, who notably hosted seances in the White House after the death of her son Willy.",
        "answer": "Mary Todd Lincoln"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's wife, Sally Hayfron, was imprisoned for saying that Queen Elizabeth II, \"Can go to hell.\" This ZANLA leader compromised in a cease-fire with Christopher Soames known as the Lancaster House Agreement. Many Ndebele [[nn-deh-BEH-leh]] were killed in this man's Gukurahundi, and he led the North Korea-trained 5th Brigade. This ZANU-PF leader gave a speech at Rufaro Stadium to announce the renaming of his nation in 1980. Canaan Banana preceded, for ten points, what man who served for thirty years as president of Zimbabwe?",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Christopher Soames was the last governor of this British Crown colony. This de jure colony declared independence in 1965, becoming an unrecognized state, before officially being recognized as Zimbabwe in 1980.",
        "answer": "Colony of Southern Rhodesia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Under this man, Mexican films and songs gained popularity as part of the Yu-Mex craze, and this man used a yacht named Peace Ship Galeb. This man signed the Treaty of Bled with Georgi Dimitrov and was the first head of the Non-Aligned Movement. This man sent a letter to Stalin ordering him to stop sending assassins and threatening that he would need only one killer to assassinate Stalin. Despite reforms, this man opposed the Croatian Spring. For ten points, name this Partisan leader and president of Yugoslavia.",
        "answer": [
          "Marshal Josip Broz Tito",
          "Tito"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "From 2009 to 2011, this man who served as president of Egypt for thirty years was also secretary-general of the Non-Aligned Movement.",
        "answer": "Hosni Mubarak"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this battle, Samuel Heintzelman was tasked with attacking Sudley Springs Ford. The Enterprise provided balloon reconnaissance at this battle which included fighting at Blackburn’s Ford. Joseph Johnston’s arrival contributed to Irwin McDowell’s defeat at this battle, which was the subject of a telegraph sent to Lincoln declaring “The day is lost. Save Washington and the remnants of this army.\" Fought in July of 1861 in Prince William County, Virginia, for ten points, what was this battle sometimes named for nearby Manassas?",
        "answer": [
          "First Battle of Bull Run",
          "First Battle of Manassas before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joseph Johnston was seriously wounded during this 1862 battle in Northern Virginia, also known as the Battle of Fair Oaks Station, after which Robert E. Lee took command of the Confederate army.",
        "answer": "Battle of Seven Pines"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Regarding people and events surrounding the Iraq War, name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about Regarding people and events surrounding the Iraq War, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Year in which the war started with an American-led coalition invading Iraq.",
          "answer": "2003"
        },
        {
          "question": "Iraqi capital which fell to coalition forces less than three weeks after the war started.",
          "answer": "Baghdad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word phrase displayed on the USS Abraham Lincoln during a post-war speech by George W. Bush.",
          "answer": "Mission Accomplished"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party of Saddam Hussein and Syrian president Hafez al-Assad.",
          "answer": "Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term given to French Fries in Congressional cafeterias after France did not join in the invasion of Iraq.",
          "answer": "Freedom Fries"
        },
        {
          "question": "Iraqi prime minister between 2006 and 2014 who was interviewed by the CIA.",
          "answer": "Nouri al-Maliki"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rhode Island senator, the only Republican to vote against the declaration of war.",
          "answer": "Lincoln Chafee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presidential envoy who announced at the capture of Saddam Hussein, \"Ladies and gentlemen, we got him.\"",
          "answer": "Paul Bremer 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Years of Lead",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country in which the Years of Lead took place, in which terrorists killed civilians in cities like Florence.",
          "answer": [
            "Italy",
            "Italian Republic",
            "Italia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern region in which the Piazza Fontana bombing took place in Milan.",
          "answer": [
            "Lombardy",
            "Lombardia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian Democrat prime minister who was kidnapped and killed in 1978 following a failed papal mediation mission.",
          "answer": "Aldo Moro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Terrorist group that kidnapped that leader and was led by Mario Moretti.",
          "answer": [
            "Red Brigades",
            "BR",
            "Brigate Rosse"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City where 85 people were killed at the Centrale railway station in a 1980 bombing.",
          "answer": [
            "Bologna",
            "Bononia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. Army officer who was kidnapped in 1981 and was rescued a year later by the NOCS in Padua.",
          "answer": "James Lee Dozier"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of large factory strikes in 1969 and 1970 that led to the Years of Lead.",
          "answer": [
            "Hot Autumn",
            "Autunno caldo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Policeman, the first victim of the Years of Lead, who was killed while serving during a communist demonstration.",
          "answer": "Antonio Annarumma 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Politics in 21st Century Latin America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Socialist president of Venezuela elected in 1999 whose policies led to a shaky economy in the 2010s.",
          "answer": "Hugo Chávez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Successor to that president, whose 2018 election results were contested by conservative opponent Juan Guaidó.",
          "answer": "Nicolás Maduro"
        },
        {
          "question": "First indigenous South American president who led Bolivia between 2006 and 2019.",
          "answer": [
            "Evo Morales",
            "Juan Evo Morales Ayma"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Crop used to produce an illegal stimulant, which was legalized in an attempt to help poor farmers in Bolivia.",
          "answer": "Coca plant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorful term used to denote Latin America's abandonment of neoliberal leaders during its \"Turn to the Left.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Pink Tide",
            "Marea Rosa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ecuadorian president and founder of the PAIS [[pah-EES]] Alliance, whose vice president was Lenin Moreno.",
          "answer": "Rafael Correa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Populist leader of Argentina who used the Relato K system to spread propaganda to the masses.",
          "answer": "Cristina Fernández de Kirchner"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Guyana whose People's Progressive Party has been accused of advancing socialist policies.",
          "answer": "Irfaan Ali 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Under First Sergeant Robert John Simmons, this group stopped a Confederate advance at the Battle of Grimball's Landing. This group's second-in-command, Edward Needles Hallowell, was appointed by Governor John Albion Andrew. Frederick (20 pts)",
        "Douglass's sons were among the first to join this group, which trained at Camp Meigs [[MIGS]]. Augustus Saint-Gaudens [[GAW-dens]] sculpted a memorial to this group, which executed a frontal assault against Fort (10 pts)",
        "Wagner. For ten points, name this group led by Robert Gould Shaw, the first Black regiment recruited in the Northern states during the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "54th Massachusetts Infantry Regiment",
        "the Glory Regiment"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In 2002, forgeries of this man’s art peddled by con-artist Alfredo Ramos Martínez led to his investigation and arrest by the FBI. This artist worked with (*) Andy Warhol on a painting called Olympics, with Warhol painting Olympic rings accompanied by this artist’s stenciling of African mask-like heads. This artist’s painting of a (*) skull, Untitled, was sold for over $110 million, the most expensive painting by an American artist. For ten points, name this New York graffiti artist who died in 1988 from a heroin overdose."
      ],
      "answer": "Jean-Michel Basquiat"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this region, members of the Irob ruled as governors of Agame [[ah-GAH- meh]]. This region’s capital city of Mekelle [[meh-KEH-leh]] was home to the royal residence of Yohannes IV. The Derg faced a rebellion led by this region’s namesake (20 pts)",
        "“People’s Liberation Front,” which has more recently been involved in a conflict with the government of Abiy Ahmed following a disputed 2020 election. North of the (10 pts)",
        "Amhara region and south of Eritrea is, for ten points, what region involved in an ongoing conflict with the Ethiopian government?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tigray Region",
        "Region One"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In 1955, Acharya Shantisagar notably performed a version of this practice called sallekhana, which was banned by the Rajasthan High Court in 2015. In Baha'i, this practice begins at the end of the Intercalary Days and ends with the festival of (*) Naw-Ruz, lasting for 19 days. In Islam, this practice begins at suhur, and ends at iftar. This practice is observed during religious occasions such as (*) Lent, Yom Kippur, and Ramadan. For ten points, name this religious practice in which people refrain from eating and drinking."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fasting",
        "Sawm",
        "Siyam",
        "equivalents such as not eating 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Under this monarch, Alexander Bach instituted a period of neo-absolutism. A high collar this man was wearing likely saved him from being killed in an assassination attempt conducted by the nationalist János [[YAH-noash]] (20 pts)",
        "Libényi. The combined forces of Napoleon III and Victor Emmanuel II defeated this man's forces at Solferino. The suicide of this (10 pts)",
        "man’s son, Crown Prince Rudolf, left this man's nephew as his would-be successor. Ruling for nearly 68 years, for ten points, who was this Austrian emperor?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Franz Joseph I",
        "Francis Joseph I",
        "Ferenc József",
        "Franz Josef Karl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Mangosuthu Buthelezi left this party to found the Inkatha Freedom Party. This party led the Defiance Campaign against Unjust Laws after another party passed legislation including the Group Areas Act. This party, whose youth division operated the paramilitary (20 pts)",
        "“Spear of the Nation,” was banned by the C. R. Swart government following the (10 pts)",
        "Soweto uprising against the mandatory use of Afrikaans in schools. For ten points, name this prominent South African party of Jacob Zuma, Thabo Mbeki, and Nelson Mandela."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "African National Congress",
        "ANC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The federal government forced a mandatory livestock reduction on these people, whom Thomas Henry Dodge represented. John MacRae Washington helped negotiate with this tribe, and its leader, Narbona, signed the Bear Springs Treaty. (20 pts)",
        "Kit Carson brought these people to Bosque Redondo in the Long Walk. Led by Barboncito and Manuelito, this tribe was integrated into the (10 pts)",
        "army by Philip Johnston as code-talkers. Calling themselves the Diné, for ten points, what is this Southwest American tribe, the largest to be federally recognized?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Navajo or Naabeehó",
        "Diné before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As a young intelligence officer, this man was supported by explorer Fridtjof Nansen [[FRIT-yof NAHN-sehn]] to write a report on the League of Nations’s relief in Kharkiv, Ukraine. Curt Brauer ordered King (20 pts)",
        "Haakon VII to appoint this man as prime minister, leading to the monarch’s establishment of a government-in-exile in the U.K. The name of this leader of the Nasjonal (10 pts)",
        "Samling became synonymous with being a traitor to one’s home country. For ten points, name this fascist prime minister of Norway who collaborated with the Nazi government."
      ],
      "answer": "Vidkun Quisling 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 6"
    }
  ]
}